Who's going to fill that number nine
role? Ali, what have you seen from
Raphinha so far scoring five goals in
three games?
>> Well, the answer is very simple.
Raphinha is going to fill that role. And
if it's not Raphinha, this team has
enough fluidity and players to
interchange where others are going to
score goals. But the performances of
Raphinha and in terms of how he's
playing the position, I'll ask quite
frankly, today in his first goal, the
way he takes this chance, what center
forward, what out and out striker, what
number nine in the world could do this
better than what he just did here? The
movement without the ball to make
himself available and then in a tight
space getting around the defender and
once he is face to face with a
goalkeeper,
finding the calmness to then find the
back of the net. Again,
what striker in the world, you pick it,
whoever, could do that better than what
Raphinha did just there?
I don't think you can find one.
>> I can only think of one that has the
similar movement and skill set to pull
that off. But it goes to what you're
saying that it's so scarce in the That
that one is Kylian Mbappé. He's the only
one I could think of that would come
close to that move, finish it off in the
same way. But I agree with what Ali's
saying. Raphinha has not shown you or
given you any indication that he's not
comfortable as playing in that number
nine position. And the fluidity that
Ali's talking about, Barcelona's going
to do this. They're going to overwhelm
the majority of the opponents they play
in La Liga. So whoever that number nine
is is going to get opportunities. Even
if you're not the number nine. Ansu Fati
comes on, he gets opportunities in
around the box. Gavi's in there, he gets
opportunities in around the box. Lamine,
you don't even need to doubt Lamine's
greatness. They're going to get those
opportunities and so will Gabriel Jesus
when he comes in. That's not the issue
here.
Raphinha is not the doubt. Not against
Elche, not against the likes of Rayo
Vallecano. It's when you get to the
Champions League, when you get to
the type of opponent who is going to sit
back, going to pressure you a bit more,
going to make it a bit more ugly. What
type of forward are we going to see?
That's what we were measuring Raphinha,
but right now
Pichichi race, being the leader, you
can't ask Raphinha to do anything more.
Anything you thought he would have been
able to achieve, he surpassed that
already in these three games.
>> You saw that heat map. We were used to
see Raphinha playing more on the
left-hand side of Barcelona's attack.
Now, with this new task
>> Mhm.
>> he's finding spaces that he used to find
he would when he would play in England
from the right-hand side cutting in into
the center of the attack of in this case
Barcelona. Now,
if you take a look at the second goal,
you spoke about that connection with
Anthony Gordon. What did you see from
Raphinha in that second goal?
>> That he is playing the number nine
position in a non-traditional way. His
movement in this goal is not a number
nine movement. He drops to the top of
the 18-yard box. A number nine usually
will go either to the near post or the
far post or split center back. But when
he drops and then recognizes that there
is a chance to be overlapping, you don't
see number nines overlapping inside the
18-yard box. You can go far back as
Ronaldo phenomenon. Is he overlapping?
No, he's not. You can go to Erling
Haaland. Is he overlapping? No, he's
not. Robert Lewandowski, who was part of
this team. Is he overlapping inside the
18-yard box? No, he's not because
they're going to find central positions
because their movement is as soon as
Anthony Gordon starts cutting with the
ball inside, you try to find the space.
And where is the space going to be?
Usually for a number nine, it's
somewhere in that central position. So,
you're going to go near post, you're
going to go far post, you're going to
take the defender away, and then come
back, try to split the center back. But
when he drops off in the manner in which
he did there, it's non-traditional
[clears throat]
play. Why is that difficult to defend as
the center back? Because as a center
back, you're used to that movement, near
post, far post, or somewhere in between.
When he drops off, you kind of like,
"Okay, I guess we've done our work
because now he's not in our space. He
would be in the trailing central
midfielder."
But, the recognition then to do the
overlapping run that is more of a wide
player sort of move, guess what? Now,
the center back can't get there in time,
and the recovering central midfielder
can't get there in time, either. And
again, more important than anything
else, while he is playing the position
in a non-traditional way, what is very
traditional is that he's finding the
final touch. He's finding the finish.
And so, it's difficult to defend because
you can't quite expect the movement from
him. It's not a traditional number nine
movement, and yet he's finding the
finish as a number nine would. He right
now is playing at an extremely high
level.
>> You don't see number nines doing this.
I
It's not a natural movement. It's a wide
player movement. And it's the
recognition of even when he drops off to
the top of the 18-yard box, it's a not a
number nine movement. So, it's
non-traditional play, but it's
non-traditional play that works for him,
and then everybody else recognizes that
if he's taking himself out of a central
position, that's why Roldri appears
there. That's why Fermín López appears
there, or whoever it is that is
appearing on the other side.
This takes some recognition from the
team, and it takes some understanding as
to
what the player rotations are going to
be, but more importantly, it takes, I
think, instinct from Raphinha that he's
playing a position that is not natural
to him, but he's playing it
to his level of understanding as to how
he is going to find himself in open
position, and he's scoring goals. He's
being very efficient, very effective
with his chances and his movement. He's
given a clinic as to how to play the
position.
>> just end with this. It's very
infectious. We usually when we we speak
about the how infectious Raphinha is,
it's in how he presses, how he defends
for the group. And if you see him doing
that, you follow suit. The movement
offensively is the same thing. When you
see that movement, you have no choice if
you're in that front line but say, "I
can't just stand still. I have to myself
move and join."
>> 12 goals this team in three matches.
>> Yeah.
>> So,
goals are not going to be a problem for
Barcelona.
>> First couple of seasons under Hansi
Flick, Barca scored in average almost
100 goals per season in all comps. Maybe
this makes them even more dangerous than
what they were in the first couple of
seasons under Hansi Flick. 11.6 million
dollars seems like a bargain for any
player. But for Gabriel Jesus, who's
played less than 35 games league games
in the last two seasons, has scored less
than 15 goals in the last 2 years.
What would be his role, Ale, in this
team?
>> A very limited one.
Uh especially when you see what the
other guys that are playing in the front
line for Barcelona look like and the
sort of job that they have done over the
first uh three matches. Anthony Gordon
has been outstanding. Lamine Yamal
scored a couple of goals today. Raphinha
we already talked about. Fermín López. I
mean, look, it's just
I
I look at Gabriel Jesus and while he may
be a nice piece to have, I don't think
that he is going to have
I disagree with Hansi Flick. I don't
think he's going to have a very
important role for Barcelona. He'll have
a role that has a lot of Copa del Rey
written all over it. Uh early days of
Champions League written all over it.
That's the sort of role that I see from
Gabriel Jesus coming off the bench,
maybe starting a game here or there,
giving a break to
one of these guys that plays in the
front line.
I don't think that if you're Barcelona
and a Barcelona fan, you're looking at a
Gabriel Jesus as a problem solver for
you. He's a nice piece to have.
>> If you're a Barcelona fan, you're
probably thinking that this is how this
is a frustrating [music]
piece to add right now. You were talking
about Julián Álvarez not too long ago.
That's what you were promised. Now, he's
29 years of age.
His best years of football are probably
behind him. His best season was with
[music] City 2021 where he scored double
digit goals, double digit assists. When
you're seeing players like Ollie Watkins
go for an extraordinary money, you're
seeing Bradley Barcola go to Liverpool
for 140, you're seeing these crazy just
unreal transfer fees and you're saying,
"Okay,
29 years of age,
maybe he's closer to the player that
played two World Cups for Brazil and had
zero goals in nine games. Could be. But
at Barcelona with the volume of football
we play, he's going to get in the
>> I thought you were making an argument
for Gabriel Jesus.
>> I am.
With the type of football that Barcelona
plays, he's going to get opportunities.
Maybe he can have a resurgence, a second
coming like Marcus Rashford did with
Barcelona.
>> He's a I think he's he's a nice piece to
have. And is a guy that every so often
may score an important goal for you,
maybe coming off the bench.
I don't think
uh Barcelona are more likely to win
Champions League right now because they
have Gabriel Jesus. Let's just say that.
>> adds depth to the
>> Yes. Yes. Absolutely.
>> roster and to your point of the fluidity
of this game,
that fits his style of play. He's not a
set number nine, he's not a winger.
>> And he presses
>> play He's a forward. He
He's like Marcus Rashford, right? Who
played every single spot on the field in
the attack. He might be able to do that
if if he's fit to play. That's been the
massive question mark with Gabriel Jesus
in the last couple of years.
>> are important. Marcus Rashford, double
digit goals and assists for Barcelona.
And if you go back to the Champions
League game where they played against
Newcastle, it's Marcus Rashford's goals
that gave Barcelona the win there. So,
these type of players can be important.